<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>kikitux.net</title>
 <link href="http://kikitux.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://kikitux.net"/>
 <updated>2013-02-28T13:06:24+13:00</updated>
 <id>http://kikitux.net</id>
 <author>
   <name>Alvaro Miranda</name>
   <email>kikitux@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Public Yum for Oracle Linux 6.4 is out</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/ol/public-yum-for-oracle-linux-64-is-out.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-28T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/ol/public-yum-for-oracle-linux-64-is-out</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux 6.4 public-yum channel is out, happy updating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New kernel UEK also, 2.6.39-400&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-28 at 1.03.12 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-28 at 1.03.12 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Getting started with Oracle Linux</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/ol/getting-started-with-oracle-linux.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-27T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/ol/getting-started-with-oracle-linux</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will be very basic, the goal is to end with the iso of Oracle Linux on your local machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The version we will use here, will be Oracle Linux 6.3 x86_64, at some point will update the post to cover OL 6.4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will be divided in the following parts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 Some general information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 Downloading OL6 ISO from the mirrors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 Downloading OL6 ISO from e-delivery.oracle.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 Patches or yum repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Some general information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good source of information is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikis.oracle.com/display/oraclelinux/Home&quot;&gt;Oracle Linux Wiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will find useful information written from people close to Support, Marketing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle is a big company, so expect them to be sometimes slow, or some times you won't understand them at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is not just a Linux Company, is a end-to-end, or disk-to-app company. They do a lot of things, and keep buying companies to expand they offer. Real business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle, keep changing all the time, and the way they go to the market, keep changing also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be very frustrating for the new starterts, and a total challenge for the experts, but is part of the magic to work with Oracle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is not secret formula, there is no single source of truth with Oracle, what may work for someone, may not work at all for someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more important, what used to work, now doesn't work at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work with oracle require, test, test, test, test, test, test, test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best advise that I can share is, be nice, gentle and keep what you do under control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a bit messy in the test environment, then your dev environment will be a bit dirty, and when the time to push something into production came, you will be forced to acknowledge to put something in production that is not 100% nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may sound silly, and you may be thinking 'whatever, I am the linux ninja in my company' but in the Oracle world, the idea is keep the business running, keep the system up and running, and get uptime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I will share, a clean way, and will try to share my expertise here, and If you can use anything of this, I will be happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;/about.html&quot;&gt;about page&lt;/a&gt;, you will find my name, couple of links and my email. All feedback is welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Downloading OL6 ISO from the mirrors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Oracle Wiki, we can find there is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikis.oracle.com/display/oraclelinux/Downloading+Oracle+Linux&quot;&gt;list of mirrors&lt;/a&gt; from where download Oracle Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very nice, as you may have a mirror close to you, and it will be faster and simpler than using the Oracle Way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I am writing this, the mirror available are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Country     Mirror 
AU          AARnet  
                    http://mirror.aarnet.edu.au/pub/oraclelinux/
                    ftp://mirror.aarnet.edu.au/pub/oraclelinux/

DE 
            GWDG
                    http://ftp5.gwdg.de/pub/linux/oracle/
                    ftp://ftp5.gwdg.de/pub/linux/oracle/
                    rsync://ftp5.gwdg.de/pub/linux/oracle/

DE          NetCologne
                    http://mirror.netcologne.de/oracle-linux/
                    ftp://mirror.netcologne.de/oracle-linux/
                    rsync://mirror.netcologne.de/oracle-linux/ 
DK 
            dotsrc.org
                    http://mirrors.dotsrc.org/oracle-linux/
                    ftp://mirrors.dotsrc.org/oracle-linux/ 
FR 
            Institut de recherche et coordination acoustique/musique
                    http://mirrors.ircam.fr/pub/oraclelinux/
                    ftp://mirrors.ircam.fr/pub/oraclelinux/
                    rsync://mirrors.ircam.fr/pub/oraclelinux/
IE 
            HEAnet
                    http://ftp.heanet.ie/mirrors/oracle-linux/
                    ftp://ftp.heanet.ie/mirrors/oracle-linux/
                    rsync://ftp.heanet.ie/mirrors/oracle-linux/
PL 
            University of Warsaw - ICM
                    http://ftp.icm.edu.pl/pub/Linux/dist/oracle-linux/
                    ftp://ftp.icm.edu.pl/pub/Linux/dist/oracle-linux/
                    rsync://ftp.icm.edu.pl/pub/Linux/dist/oracle-linux/
UK 
            linux.org.uk
                    http://ftp.linux.org.uk/pub/distributions/enterprise/
                    ftp://ftp.linux.org.uk/pub/distributions/enterprise/
                    rsync://zeniv.linux.org.uk/distributions/enterprise/
US          Wimmekes.net
                    http://mirrors.wimmekes.net/pub/OracleLinux/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With great surprise I found this information when I had to download couple of isos.. I am located in NZ, and the internet here.. you get the idea.. so the mirror in Australia did the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an additional tip, the mirror on Wimmekes.net is one of the Senior VP of Oracle Linux, so chances that something show up there before the public-yum.oracle.com are very high time by time.. When that happen, he will update &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.oracle.com/wim/&quot;&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Downloading OL6 ISO from e-delivery.oracle.com&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle is a big company, because of this, you need to be prepared to login to some portals, click on some agreements (export, security, etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to avoid that, use wget/curl/script go with the mirrors, and all happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official source for distribution of Oracle Linux, OracleVM, and OracleVM Templates is on &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com/linux&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com/linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For other products you may find the source could be &lt;a href=&quot;http://otn.oracle.com&quot;&gt;otn.oracle.com&lt;/a&gt;, or in form of patches in &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.oracle.com&quot;&gt;support&lt;/a&gt;, or the general &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point you should register an account to become your oracle single sign on (sso) account, this account will be the same, for &lt;a href=&quot;http://otn.oracle.com&quot;&gt;otn.oracle.com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.oracle.com/&quot;&gt;forums&lt;/a&gt;, so when you get some time, create one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you got to &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com/linux&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com/linux&lt;/a&gt; you will see this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.27.31 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.27.31 PM.png' max-width='70%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you click on Sign in / Register button, you will redirected to the actual login / register page&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.29.01 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.29.01 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, highlighted in the red square is the part of the register. Follow the instructions, and you will be done with your account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point it will ask if you will like to get some emails with information. I find to be very nice the emails that oracle sent, so don't be shy and mark all the areas you are interested in. You will have the chance to opt out of those mails later if you don't like them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the account created, you can login.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the export regulation agrement, you will be on the main menu of &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com/linux&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com/linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.34.07 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.34.07 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your window is not the same, please check on top you are on Cloud Linux&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.34.55 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.34.55 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If not, probably you are in &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com&lt;/a&gt; instead of &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com/linux&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com/linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then select the version and the architecture, here 6.3 x86_64 bits and click on GO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.36.53 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.36.53 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can click on the Oracle Linux Release 6 Update 3 Media Pack for x86_64 (64 bit) or select the radio button, scroll down and click on Continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you should see 6 options for Oracle Linux 6.3 x86_64&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.39.34 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.39.34 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top Left of the option, there is a README button, in case of doubt, or just because you want to check, click on that, and have a look at the readme.  From here you have the option to download the isos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux Release 6 Update 3 for x86_64 (64 Bit)                       V33411-01   3.5G&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  The DVD to install the Oracle Linux 6.3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux Release 6 Update 3 Boot iso image for x86_64 (64 bit)        V33412-01   198M&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  The boot.iso image to use this same iso to boot from hard disk or network (ftp, http or nfs)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux Release 6 Update 3 source DVD 1                              V33413-01   3.1G&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux Release 6 Update 3 source DVD 2                              V33414-01   1.7G&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  The sources, source rpm of the content of the media&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux Release 6 Update 3 UEK Boot ISO image for x86_64 (64 bit)    V34537-01   196M&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  A second boot.iso, this one is to be able to use btrfs as a filesystem option during the install.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the README are the instructions on how to use the UEK Boot ISO image for x86_64, those instruction are are very clear on how to prepare a network point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a separate post, I will cover how to do this, and how to create a new Oracle Linux 6.3 ISO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you will like to try this, without all the problems to extract the iso, modified, recreate one, you may try an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/waht5bii6nchkrd/OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-btrfs.iso&quot;&gt;ISO image that I have created&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other resources, check what I have shared &lt;a href=&quot;/dropbox&quot;&gt;on dropbox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main difference is, you can actually choose btrfs from the installer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will cover this option, and some examples on btrfs in a separate post, however, if you google about btrfs you will see all the nice features this have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Patches or yum repository&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux is one of those RedHat derivates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won't go deep on here, and won't compare with CentOS or other RedHat derivates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to Oracle Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux is based on RPM, that is RedHat Package Management. The tool to use RPM is the command rpm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RPM works very great that is used by other Linux distros (like Suse) and even some other Unix (AIX use some packages on RPM format).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, the rpm had a downside, that was the dependency nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You wanted to install patch A, and you found patch A, require patch B, and patch B required patch C and D, and so on..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may ended downloading 15 patches on different versions to then find the new versions conflict with the existing ones due versions, so you had to say I will update the installed one (and end updating say 50 rpms) or re-download rpms again to match the ones installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real 'fun'&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, the guys at Yellow Dog came with the YUM, Yellow Dog Update Manager, YUM, that basically used an external database to track versions and dependencies and with a repository, it will download and take of the nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the version 4 of the distro, YUM was external. Once the system was installed you can use it.. very nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For version 5 of the distro, the YUM came included at the moment of the install, so once the OS was installed, you pointed the new fresh machine to a yum repo, and you can update immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the version 6, now this is cool, you can point to a yum repository during the install (interactive by a menu, or automated by a kickstart file) and instead of using the packages of the DVD or the network share, it will install the updates one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may sound similar, but let's check on times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On version 5, say install 20 minutes, boot, full update 20 minutes, boot. Total 40 minutes and 1 reboot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On version 6, say install 20 mins.. boot.. done.. Updated. Total 20 mins no reboot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For oracle linux, the public source of repo is &lt;a href=&quot;http://public-yum.oracle.com&quot;&gt;public-yum.oracle.com&lt;/a&gt; in the web page are the instructions, and work very very nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a new installed machine, with direct access to internet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Oracle Linux 6

# cd /etc/yum.repos.d
# wget http://public-yum.oracle.com/public-yum-ol6.repo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With no direct access to internet, say with a proxy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Oracle Linux 6

# cd /etc/yum.repos.d
# http_proxy=http://proxy:3128 wget http://public-yum.oracle.com/public-yum-ol6.repo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just replace proxy:3128 with the correct url of the proxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a later post I will post information how to use an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kikitux/public-yum-downloader&quot;&gt;script I wrote to create a local yum repo from public-yum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this you have now all the information to download your Oracle Linux iso, and keep the system updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alvaro.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>zsync</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/zsync/zsync.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-25T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/zsync/zsync</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been testing zsync and it's great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href=&quot;/zsync&quot;&gt;download from here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's see an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have 2 isos, the normal oracle linux 6.3 dvd and one modified to be able to use btrfs from the installer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both dvd are just the same, few bits different, according to zsync, 97% the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download the normal dvd iso&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;retina:tmp mirandaa$ zsync http://mirandaa00/stage/iso/OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-dvd.iso.zsync
#################### 100.0% 0.0 kBps DONE    

No relevent local data found - I will be downloading the whole file. If that's not what you want, CTRL-C out. You should specify the local file is the old version of the file to download with -i (you might have to decompress it with gzip -d first). Or perhaps you just have no data that helps download the file
downloading from http://mirandaa00/stage/iso/OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-dvd.iso:
#################### 100.0% 102257.5 kBps DONE     

verifying download...checksum matches OK
used 0 local, fetched 3675326805
retina:tmp mirandaa$ ls
OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-dvd.iso
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;let's move the normal dvd into the btrfs one&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;retina:tmp mirandaa$ mv OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-dvd.iso OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-btrfs.iso 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let's use zsync to update the normal dvd into the modified one&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;retina:tmp mirandaa$ zsync http://mirandaa00/stage/iso/OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-btrfs.iso.zsync
#################### 100.0% 0.0 kBps DONE    

reading seed file OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-btrfs.iso: *************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************Read OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-btrfs.iso. Target 97.1% complete.      
downloading from http://mirandaa00/stage/iso/OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-btrfs.iso:
#################### 100.0% 9790.2 kBps DONE      

verifying download...checksum matches OK
used 3598319616 local, fetched 108470391
retina:tmp mirandaa$ 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alvaro&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>OL6 Certified Implementation Specialist</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/cert/ol6-certified-implementation-specialist.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-25T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/cert/ol6-certified-implementation-specialist</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back on December I took the 1z1-460 exam for Oracle Linux 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday, got a letter from Oracle with a printed certificate, quite nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks Oracle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;digital&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/OEL 6 Implementation Specialist 2012.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/OEL 6 Implementation Specialist 2012.png&quot; max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;paper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/OEL 6 Implementation Specialist 2012 - carton.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/OEL 6 Implementation Specialist 2012 - carton.jpg&quot; max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>zfs data protection</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/zfs/zfs-data-protection.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-22T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/zfs/zfs-data-protection</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When ZFS for MAC came out with ZEVO, I did run to get the software and being used for about a year or so..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you stay away enabling dedup, the filesystem run very good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I did format a 500gb disk to use for some VM's in my laptop. If those VM's die, it's ok, I usually have VirtualBox appliances, and backup of the software, so I could be able to start from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I will like to protect the whole disk file without having to backup, in case I drop the hdd (again), and some blocks came corrupted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did use the zfs option to have more copies stored on disk, in this case 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Disk just formatted&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;retina:~ mirandaa$ zfs get copies
NAME      PROPERTY  VALUE   SOURCE
zfs500gb  copies    1       local&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Enable the option copy=2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;retina:~ mirandaa$ zfs set copies=2 zfs500gb
retina:~ mirandaa$ zfs get copies
NAME      PROPERTY  VALUE   SOURCE
zfs500gb  copies    2       local&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;let's write some data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;100MB&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;retina:~ mirandaa$ df -h /Volumes/zfs500gb/
Filesystem   Size   Used  Avail Capacity iused     ifree %iused  Mounted on
/dev/disk2  457Gi  354Ki  457Gi     1%      70 957873343    0%   /Volumes/zfs500gb
retina:~ mirandaa$ dd if=/dev/zero of=/Volumes/zfs500gb/file bs=1024000 count=100
100+0 records in
100+0 records out
102400000 bytes transferred in 0.067305 secs (1521435685 bytes/sec)
retina:~ mirandaa$ df -h /Volumes/zfs500gb/
Filesystem   Size   Used  Avail Capacity iused     ifree %iused  Mounted on
/dev/disk2  457Gi  196Mi  457Gi     1%      71 957472837    0%   /Volumes/zfs500gb
retina:~ mirandaa$ ls -alh /Volumes/zfs500gb/file 
-rw-r--r--  1 mirandaa  staff    98M 22 Feb 13:31 /Volumes/zfs500gb/file
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1GB&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;retina:~ mirandaa$ dd if=/dev/zero of=/Volumes/zfs500gb/file bs=1024000 count=1000
1000+0 records in
1000+0 records out
1024000000 bytes transferred in 32.551312 secs (31458025 bytes/sec)
retina:~ mirandaa$ df -h /Volumes/zfs500gb/
Filesystem   Size   Used  Avail Capacity iused     ifree %iused  Mounted on
/dev/disk2  457Gi  1.9Gi  455Gi     1%      71 953981891    0%   /Volumes/zfs500gb
retina:~ mirandaa$ ls -alh /Volumes/zfs500gb/file 
-rw-r--r--  1 mirandaa  staff   977M 22 Feb 13:32 /Volumes/zfs500gb/file
retina:~ mirandaa$ 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system, is transparent, just just get more used space, and less free space:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='/images/kikitux.net 2013-02-22 at 1.42.08 PM.png' &gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/kikitux.net 2013-02-22 at 1.42.08 PM.png'  max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='/images/kikitux.net 2013-02-22 at 1.41.49 PM.png' &gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/kikitux.net 2013-02-22 at 1.41.49 PM.png'  max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an excerpt from an oracle post &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.oracle.com/relling/entry/zfs_copies_and_data_protection&quot;&gt;https://blogs.oracle.com/relling/entry/zfs_copies_and_data_protection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Using Copies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To change the numbers of data copies, set the copies property. For example, suppose I have a zpool named &quot;zwimming.&quot; The default number of data copies is 1. But you can change that to 2 quite easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# zfs set copies=2 zwimming
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The copies property works for all new writes, so I recommend that you set that policy when you create the file system or immediately after you create a zpool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can verify the copies setting by looking at the properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# zfs get copies zwimming
NAME      PROPERTY  VALUE     SOURCE
zwimming  copies    2         local
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ZFS will account for the space used. For example, suppose I create three new file systems and copy some data to them. You can then see that the space used reflects the number of copies. If you use quotas, then the copies will be charged against the quotas, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# zfs create -o copies=1 zwimming/single
# zfs create -o copies=2 zwimming/dual
# zfs create -o copies=3 zwimming/triple
# cp -rp /usr/share/man1 /zwimming/single
# cp -rp /usr/share/man1 /zwimming/dual
# cp -rp /usr/share/man1 /zwimming/triple
# zfs list -r zwimming                                                       
NAME              USED  AVAIL  REFER  MOUNTPOINT
zwimming         48.2M   310M  33.5K  /zwimming
zwimming/dual    16.0M   310M  16.0M  /zwimming/dual
zwimming/single  8.09M   310M  8.09M  /zwimming/single
zwimming/triple  23.8M   310M  23.8M  /zwimming/triple
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes sense. Each file system has one, two, or three copies of the data and will use correspondingly one, two, or three times as much space to store the data.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>link example</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/link-example.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-22T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/link-example</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/meminfo.png&gt;&lt;img src=https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/meminfo.png max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>SQL Staments</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/sql/sql-staments.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-21T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/sql/sql-staments</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Data manipulation language (DML)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;SELECT
INSERT
UPDATE
DELETE
MERGE
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Data definition language (DDL)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;CREATE
ALTER
DROP
RENAME
TRUNCATE
COMMENT
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Data control language (DCL)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;GRANT
REVOKE
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Transaction control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;COMMIT
ROLLBACK
SAVEPOINT
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>HR Schema</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/oracle/hr-schema.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-21T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/oracle/hr-schema</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;HR Schema in Oracle sample database&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/oracle/hr.png' &gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/oracle/hr.png'  max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alvaro&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>OSX server and ruby dependencies</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/osx/osx-server-and-ruby-dependencies.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-14T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/osx/osx-server-and-ruby-dependencies</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a person who likes to have backups, and be on the bleeding edge most of the time, testing, checking.. learnings.. even when that mean break my database box at the office and also found that yesterdy update of ruby at my mac mini server &lt;a href=&quot;http://support.apple.com/kb/TS4042&quot;&gt;broke the ruby dependencies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wondering how long it will take break my mac server anyways.. took, 2 days.. :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/osx/Server.png&quot; title=&quot;Osx Server&quot; alt=&quot;OSX Server&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alvaro&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>