<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>kikitux.net</title>
 <link href="http://kikitux.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://kikitux.net"/>
 <updated>2013-03-10T17:46:22+13:00</updated>
 <id>http://kikitux.net</id>
 <author>
   <name>Alvaro Miranda</name>
   <email>kikitux@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Installing Oracle Linux 6</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/ol/installing-oracle-linux-6.html"/>
   <updated>2013-03-02T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/ol/installing-oracle-linux-6</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post will cover a basic installation of Oracle Linux 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this task, we will use a virtual box guest, however, the same idea apply to any other virtualization technology or bare metal install on a physical server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before we start&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Release notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ISO / DVD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installation Method&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installation Media&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kickstart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Before we start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;/about&quot;&gt;about page&lt;/a&gt; are few lines about who I am, my email and link to linkedin. All feedback is good feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me share few lines about Linux and myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the year 2003, RedHat took the first RHCE exam in Chile, RedHat 9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before that was just on the other countries like Argentina or Brazil, so this time was in Chile, quite expensive and the famous RHCE, the real deal with a lunch break in the middle and only hands on, trouble shooting and a installation request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the exam and passed, and was well expended money. After that, the market was open to me, being RHCE gave me an enormous advantage vs the other peers that were good but they weren't rhce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I got certified in RHCE got the invite to become RHCI, so from 2004 to 2011 I was an RedHat Certified Instructor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In RedHat space, I got certified in 2003 with RH9, then on 2007 with RHEL5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Oracle space, In 2007 I took the beta exam for Oracle Linux 5, and last December took the beta exam for Oracle Linux 6. Both passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you are good, and you can pass an exam, do it, it will look nice on the resume, and will help you in your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to our goal, I will be sharing here, both sides of the coin, the teorical level from being an instructor, and the Implementation and Support side of being Unix Admin with many implementations under the belt, most of them always related with Oracle products like databases and ebusiness suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have worked with Oracle in the past, you are familiar with what I am going to discuss here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have worked with any paid linux or unix, or hardware from some brands that require a minimun or supported version, you are somewhat familiar with certification matrix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certification matrix is an end-to-end matrix of versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may want to go ahead, install the latest Oracle Linux available, apply all the patches available and hand over to the dba or apps team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are using Oracle Linux, the chances that you are going to be working with enterprise grade hardware, and expensive applications are very high, in such cases better check and gather the requirement, rather than find the 6.4 Oracle Linux with kernel-uek-2.6.30-400 is not supported for that old application, or vice versa, the Oracle Linux 5.1 required to run that old application is not supported to run on that brand new hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A certification Matrix should cover:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hardware with their recommended firmware upgrades, and OS tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operating system that is supported, recommended for that hardware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operating system that is supported, certified and recommended for that application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application with their recommended patch level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me give you some examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Oracle Linux 5 came out, the installer of the Oracle Database 10.2 complained about the Version wasn't supported.
When Oracle Linux 6 came out, the page of some hardware vendor only listed some versions of Enterprise Linux 5, not 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ignore the needs of the applications, or just skip checking the supported version of the hardware, you may find later in the project that the hardware or the application is behaving poorly, or crashing, and when the application team engage the vendor, for hardware or software, they may just suggest, give a try to the version X.Y.Z of the OS, and you may need to do extra work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you deal with paid applications (Top Dollar), you will learn are some rules, not written, that the called 'best practices'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My best advice here is test, check, put on paper the versions of all the components, and in case of doubt, open a service request or support ticket with the vendor and ask the written confirmation or deny of using X.Y.Z combination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle is a big company, the chances you are going to end using Oracle products on top of the Oracle Linux are very high, and you need to double check in both sides that both layers are supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be covering some of this information for some of the products I use in later posts, but if you are going to be working and supporting Oracle Linux for Oracle Products, you should start becoming familiar with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/indexes/downloads/index-087287.html&quot;&gt;Certification Matrix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Release notes and documentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.oracle.com/cd/E37670_01/E39522/html/&quot;&gt;Release notes&lt;/a&gt;, seriously? yes, seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.oracle.com/cd/E37670_01/index.html&quot;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle is a big company, and they are very professional, you may not need at all check a single doc or release notes to get a linux installation, but at some point you should review the release notes and documentation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Oracle linux 6.4 came out, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.oracle.com/linux/entry/oracle_linux_6_4_has&quot;&gt;an oracle linux blog post&lt;/a&gt; came out&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&quot;https://oss.oracle.com/pipermail/el-errata/2013-February/003307.html&quot;&gt;announcement was done at the errata mailing list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quote of the Oracle Linux Blog post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;For further details, please see the Oracle Linux 6.4 Release Notes.

Oracle Linux customers also have access to a number of recently announced unique features/benefits, including:

Support for XFS file system: Today we also announced support for XFS file system in Oracle Linux. It is now available for customers with Premier Support subscriptions using Oracle Linux 6. Read the XFS support blog article for more details.

Ksplice offline client: We recently announced a new feature in our Ksplice service, known as the Ksplice offline client. Ksplice provides zero downtime updates for your kernel and now this new option eliminates the requirement to have a direct connection to the internet to apply Ksplice patches. Read more details in Wim Coekaerts’ blog and watch this video describing updating and patching in Oracle Linux.

DTrace for Oracle Linux: Another new addition is the general availability of DTrace for Oracle Linux. DTrace is a comprehensive dynamic tracing framework available to Oracle Linux customers. It is available to download from ULN for supported customers. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.oracle.com/cd/E37670_01/E39522/html/&quot;&gt;release note&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Table of Contents
Preface
1. New Features and Changes
1.1. Supported Kernels
1.1.1. Unbreakable Enterprise Kernel Release 2
1.2. Notable New Features
1.2.1. Xen Improvements
1.2.2. Notable New Features Available with the Red Hat Compatible Kernel
1.3. Technology Preview Features
1.4. Packages Added to the Upstream Release
1.5. Packages Modified from the Upstream Release
1.6. Packages Removed from the Upstream Release
1.7. Packages Added by Oracle
2. Fixed and Known Issues
2.1. Fixed Issues
2.2. Known Issues
3. Upgrading to Oracle Linux 6 Update 4
3.1. Supported Upgrade Paths
3.2. Obtaining Oracle Linux 6 Update 4 Packages
3.2.1. About the Unbreakable Linux Network
3.2.2. About Public Yum
3.2.3. About Oracle Linux Installation Media
3.3. Applying Updates
3.4. Upgrading Unbreakable Enterprise Kernel Release 2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are talking of minor release, from 6.3 to 6.4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For sure you can just install it, or do yum -u update in an existing Oracle Linux 6, but the release notes contain very nice information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be checking at least&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;2. Fixed and Known Issues
2.1. Fixed Issues
2.2. Known Issues
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;ISO / DVD&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chicken and the egg, what goes first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we did on a previous post, you need to &lt;a href=&quot;http://kikitux.net/ol/getting-started-with-oracle-linux.html&quot;&gt;download oracle linux&lt;/a&gt; , once you have the iso, you can start to plan the deployment of Oracle Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a single install, either physical or virtual, you can just burn the downloaded iso, or mount the iso and do a normal installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this method is not efficient if you need to perform several installations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ISO image is the starting point, as we will review in the following sections, you will be able to use several methods to start the installation, and you will able to use several methods to get the media on the client. Further more, the whole process can be automated, and instead of the normal interactive installation, can be done silent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example an installation, for an Oracle Linux 6.3 using root filesystem as btrfs, including all the packages and parameter needed to run Oracle Rac&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/wmzm9GU9E2c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;        &lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Installation Method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installation of Oracle Linux, can be divided in 2 separate tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Execution of the installed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installation of linux to the hard disk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To execute the installer you can use&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cd/dvd&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pendrive/hard drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;grub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's review this options&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;cd/dvd&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are familiar with this one, is just use the iso in a dvd, physical or virtual, and start the installer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get an DVD-RW as you may end modifying your Oracle Linux DVD to your own needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;pendrive/hard drive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can put the image of the iso in a pendrive or a harddrive and boot from an internal hard drive, lun, virtual disk or attached usb pendrive or disk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pendrive is very useful if you keep changing the kickstart file, example, you can edit the pendrive to setup the server name, network settings, then go to the server, boot, and take the files from a network share. This combination is very useful and simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;network&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can turn on a server, boot from the network and it will load the installer from the network&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;grub&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very cool, in a system that you have to reinstall for any reason, you can put an entry in grub, reboot the server, choose that option, and it will start the installer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this post, we will review cd/dvd execution of the installer. Either by full dvd or just boot.iso&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Installation Media&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the installer have been loaded, the 2nd part is to perform the installation of our OracleLinux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The binaries to perform the installation can be taken from several sources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;cd/dvd&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allow us to install from a CD or DVD, this usually goes related to boot from a cd/dvd and then install from the same media.
The best of this method is that doesn't require anything external, so you can setup a server and later take care of the network part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method, goes very well with a custom DVD, were you can place a kickstart file to automate the installation. If your company have a standard, fixed or not, you can automate the process, anything than is asked during the installation, can be automated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;pendrive/hard drive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one, allows to take the rpm from a pendrive or hard drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideal if you want to have a hard drive with the media plus some applications.The harddrive installation is very fast, as opposite to the pendrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;network&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With today networks speed, install over a network share is faster then CV/DVD or pendrive. Keep that idea on mind when you need to develop your internal standard build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the normal installation, that you boot from a DVD and give you the interactive install.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of the installation, have several questions or customisation, every one of them can be later performed in an automated way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installer is called 'anaconda' and have a predefined set of options, like the default layout for hard drive if you just select next, or the groups of packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an Oracle Database or Oracle Application, the installation layout should be something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/ 
/boot
swap
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the minimun. This is OK for dev and testing or test virtual machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more real layout for production, where our goal is uptime, is to separate those filesystem that can fill up or due heavy usage can become corrupted (due a crash, outage or run out of space)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for a production environment, a more common filesystem layout should be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/ 
/boot
/home
/tmp
/usr
/var
/var/tmp
swap
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to get the most simple approach, you may want to use Logical Volumes, that will give you a simple disk layout and the flexibility to grow those filesystem later in case you run out of space,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LVM, stand for Logical Volume, the basic idea behind this is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A physical disk (or more than one) provide PE, Physical Extend to the next layer
A Volume group is made of Physical Devices with a number of PE, and this Volume Group hold Logical Volumes.
A Logical Volume is mafe of LE, or logical extends
A filesystem is created on top of a logical volume&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://access.redhat.com/knowledge/docs/resources/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/6/html-single/Logical_Volume_Manager_Administration/images/overview/basic-lvm-volume.png&quot; alt=&quot;https://access.redhat.com/knowledge/docs/resources/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/6/html-single/Logical_Volume_Manager_Administration/images/overview/basic-lvm-volume.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, imagine you have a disk that is sda, and the 3rd partition sda3 is on fdisk as fd to mard the partition as LVM
Then you create a Volume Group called VG00, that have sda3 as member
Then you can create logical volumes and initialize those as filesystem or swap devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some tasks you can use those logical volumes as backed block deivices where is supported, like virtual machines on a desktop system to have virtual machines with XEN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to read more about this, check &lt;a href=&quot;https://access.redhat.com/knowledge/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/6/html-single/Logical_Volume_Manager_Administration/index.html&quot;&gt;RedHat 6 LVM manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to our installation, for a production environment, a more common filesystem layout using LVM should be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;first partition for
/boot, say 500 MB format as ext4

second partition for 
swap, say  4GB for most system
swap, say 16GB if your sever is over 12GB of ram and you will use Oracle DB

third partition as 
PV, the rest of the space
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, logical volumes as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/ 
/home
/tmp
/usr
/var
/var/tmp
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Kickstart&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anaconda installer, allow us during the boot pass an argument with an address where anaconda can find a kickstart file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A kickstart file is just a text file with a format with answers to each of the tasks to perform during the installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your kickstart is missing an option, then it will prompt on the console for that information, so, if you kickstart is complete, then you will get an installation, end to end un-attended, that is what more sysadmin like to have, less work, a consistent delivery of machines. The opposite of this is the lack of standard, where 10 different servers will have different selection of packages, different time zone, different layout of disks, etc. You want to stay away of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are several ways to start working with a kickstart file, the top 3 are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a kickstart based on a kickstart file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a kickstart using system-config-kickstart tool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a kickstart with just a text editor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or, of course a mix between any of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Create a kickstart based on a kickstart file&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any Oracle Linux machine, will leave /root/anaconda-ks.cfg file, that will be a template of the installation performed on that box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very nice feature and the best way to start creating a kickstart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a server or virtual machine, perform a installation according the standard you have, and at the end, you will end with a system that will be your base and a kickstart file that will allow you to create a file to re-use on new installations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Create a kickstart using system-config-kickstart tool&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a OracleLinux server, do yum install system-config-kickstart to install this tool&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then execute it as system-config-kickstart and you will be able to customise the different options and will save and create your very own kickstart file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also have the option to open a kickstart file in case you want to change or edit some options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Create a kickstart with just a text editor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you are confortable with the process, you can just use a text editor and create your very own kickstart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also valid to have scripts that create kickstart files, that is, you have a base, and your servers differ just in hostname, and network setup. Then you can create an script to create kickstart files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very nice manual and examples for kickstart files, can be found on &lt;a href=&quot;https://access.redhat.com/knowledge/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/6/html/Installation_Guide/ch-kickstart2.html&quot;&gt;Chapter 32. Kickstart Installations&lt;/a&gt; from redhat manual&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alvaro&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Creating an Oracle Linux 6 Virtualbox guest</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/vbox/creating-an-oracle-linux-6-virtualbox-guest.html"/>
   <updated>2013-03-02T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/vbox/creating-an-oracle-linux-6-virtualbox-guest</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On a previous post, we did check the way to &lt;a href=&quot;http://kikitux.net/ol/getting-started-with-oracle-linux.html&quot;&gt;download oracle linux 6 dvd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you got the iso image, let's create a virtualbox guest and create our first Oracle Linux 6 guest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Downloading Virtual Box&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good friends of Oracle Linux have been working in create hand ons lab for Oracle Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check the wiki &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikis.oracle.com/display/oraclelinux/Oracle+Linux+Hands-on+Labs&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They start from the basic that is download the Virtual Box and end with some cool hand on guided tasks, it worth have a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download virtualbox, is quite easy, go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.virtualbox.org/wiki/Downloads&quot;&gt;Virtualbox download page&lt;/a&gt; and download the software and Expansion pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.08.49 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.08.49 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download the software for your platform and install first the VirtualBox part, and then the Expansion pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you execute virtual box for the first time, you should see a window similar to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OSX&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.12.57 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.12.57 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Virtualbox networking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virtualbox provide a very powerful networking component for our virtual machines&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;there are 5 network types for virtual guests&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.19.10 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.19.10 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;not attached&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  This means the virtual nic is not connected to any particular network.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;NAT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  This is the Network Address Translation, the same kind of network that you are familiar in your home with a router for internet that give you those private address 192.168.x.x&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  This type is very useful when you want to work from the console of the virtual machine and you require the guest having access to the network or internet and you don't require the virtual machine having his own ip in the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  The virtual guest will take an ip like 10.2.0.15 and you can't reach from your computer or from any computer from the network.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bridged Adapter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  This type of networking is the most easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  You choose to bridge the virtual nic to one nic on your physical host, and will behave like any computer on the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  This is, if there is an dhcp server on the network, the virtual guest will take an IP from the network, and you will be able to ssh or connect to any application running on the virtual guest, plus the guest will have access to the network as any other machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  Keep in mind if you need to set up a proxy to reach internet, you will have to do the same on the virtual guest in order to get to internet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Internal Network&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  This type of network is like connecting the virtual guest to a switch that is not connected to any other device or network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  You will end with the virtual guest connected to the virtual switch, and will be isolated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  This type of network is very useful when you need to connect 2 or more virtual guest in a isolated network, example, Oracle RAC, 2 nodes with private interconnect&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Host-Only&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  This type of network is similar to the Internal Network, but the host machine (the real computer) will be able to connect and work with the virtual guests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  This type of network also allow create the network on the host, set up the ip you want to use, and will enable dhcp, so the guest will take an IP automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  From the settings of virtual box, go to network&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  Then click on the + sign&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.31.15 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.31.15 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  This will create a network called vboxnet0 with some default settings&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.32.39 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.32.39 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Address 192.168.56.1 (this is the IP that will be assigned to the physical host)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Netmask 255.255.255.0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DHCP disabled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;  Double click on the network, or select and click on the screwdriver, and you will be able to change the parameters or enable the DHCP for the guest&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.34.54 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.34.54 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;More about virtualbox networking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each virtualguest can have 4 virtual nics from the gui, but you always can add more from the command line&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A typical setup when you want the guest connected to the network at your home or office will be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  virtual nic 1, type Bridge
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A setup where you don't need the guest to be avaliable to the network will be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  virtual nic 1, type NAT
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A setup where you want to have the guest be able to access the network, but need some portability, example a virtual guest in a laptop, will be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  virtual nic 1, type NAT
  virtual nic 2, type Bridge  when the phyiscal host is connected to a network
                              if you are on the the go, like a demo, use Host Only
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;With this setup, the IP on the virtual nic 1, eth0 will be always the same, so you won't run in troubles or won't have to edit /etc/hosts each time you change network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A more complex but real setup, will be for example an Oracle RAC in virtual box&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  virtual nic 1, type Bridge
  virtual nic 2, type Internal Network (interconnect 1)
  virtual nic 3, type Internal Network (interconnect 2)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you are on the go, you can change nic 1 to Host Only, as the guest will be with fixed IP, the virtual machines will be reachable between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Creating the first virtual machine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the main window of virtual box, you can click on NEW, and this will lead us to create the first virtual guest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;OSX&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.16.36 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.16.36 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windows 7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/Creating_a_VirtualMachine_for_OL6_html_5c315d51.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/Creating_a_VirtualMachine_for_OL6_html_5c315d51.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or go to the menu machine, and then new&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OSX&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.48.42 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.48.42 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windows 7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/Creating_a_VirtualMachine_for_OL6_html_60b3e6e4.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/Creating_a_VirtualMachine_for_OL6_html_60b3e6e4.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a name and Select the OS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;OSX&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.50.17 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.50.17 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windows 7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/Creating_a_VirtualMachine_for_OL6_html_740f5071.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/Creating_a_VirtualMachine_for_OL6_html_740f5071.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set memory size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.51.08 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.51.08 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you are creating a virtual machine for an existing virtual hard drive select existing, otherwise, select new&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.51.44 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.51.44 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard disk format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can choose between several formats&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VDI from virtual box works just fine, and allow you increase the size of the disk, like when you expand a lun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.52.46 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.52.46 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storage on physical hard drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here you can choose between dynamic or fixed assigned&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dynamic will create an small disk, and will grow as you use more space on the virtual disk
Fixed will create the disk immediately of the size you assign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.53.56 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.53.56 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dynamic have the advantage you can make the disk to grow.
Fixed is supposed to be a bit faster as will avoid defragmentation the disk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my personal case, I always go as Dynamic, because my virtual machines have a very short life span.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here, there is no magic formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are confortable managing separate disks, like in the real world, you can setup a disk for just the OS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how much memory and how much you will need, the size will change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For just the OS, and 4GB of Swap, you can go with 16GB disk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For having say Oracle grid and Oracle database binaries installed, make the disk 32GB minimun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to have a database on disk, add more disk, but you should go with separate disk for datafiles with asm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don't want to use ASM, you should either way use a separate disk for the datafiles (and another for FRA and archivelogs)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.57.13 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 4.57.13 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Review of the normal setup of the new guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the virtual guest have been created, is time to check few options, like CPU and Network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right click on the machine, then Settings will open the settings page&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Systems - Motherboard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you will be able to change some options like you were interacting at motherboard level&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.03.08 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.03.08 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can adjust the amount of memory here&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Systems - Processor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you will be able to change some options like the number of processors/core&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.04.12 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.04.12 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Storage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On storage, you will see what looks like the controllers on a real computer/server&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first controller, is IDE, for a CD-ROM/DVD&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.06.36 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.06.36 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second controller, is SATA, for the virtual hard disk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.07.02 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.07.02 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can select the virtual hard disk, and see the size and how much is being used at the moment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also select an ssd option, and tell virtualbox the disk is on ssd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.05.36 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.05.36 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Network&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the network options, you have the chance to modify the default value of 1 nic as NAT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.08.17 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.08.17 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this particular machine, as I am home, I will use Bridge to the wifi of the mac&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.06.36 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.06.36 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Review the configuration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the machine have been setup, and we change some values from the default options, you can check on the side panel an overview of the machine&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.12.23 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.12.23 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Starting the virtual machine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Select the virtual machine, right click and start&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or, Select the virtual machine, then the green arrow on the menu&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or, double click on the virtual machine&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;all this options will start our virtual machine&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.14.19 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.14.19 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;First boot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the virtual machine is one, you should see an error that the machine doesn't have an OS installed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.16.15 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.16.15 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you just create a virtual machine, and go straight to start, it will open a dialog box to mount a DVD to install the OS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Devices menu, Select CD/DVD, Choose CD/DVD and browse for the OS you want to use&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.20.39 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.20.39 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the virtual DVD iso is on the virtual DVD, reboot the machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be done, selecting the virtual machine on virtual box, right click and reset&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.24.42 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.24.42 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you should see the welcome window for the OS install, in our case, Oracle Linux 6.3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.26.01 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/03/kikitux.net 2013-03-02 at 5.26.01 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;What's next&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installation of the Oracle Linux will be in a separate post, as will review some options we have, and won't be just Virtual Box related.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to get started, you can &lt;a href=&quot;/dropbox&quot;&gt;download one of the virtual appliances&lt;/a&gt; I have created and are shared by Dropbox&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download the file, double click, and review the options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the machine is imported, review the Options for ram, cpu, disks, and turn the machine on.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Public Yum for Oracle Linux 6.4 is out</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/ol/public-yum-for-oracle-linux-64-is-out.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-28T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/ol/public-yum-for-oracle-linux-64-is-out</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux 6.4 public-yum channel is out, happy updating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New kernel UEK also, 2.6.39-400&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-28 at 1.03.12 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-28 at 1.03.12 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Getting started with Oracle Linux</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/ol/getting-started-with-oracle-linux.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-27T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/ol/getting-started-with-oracle-linux</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will be very basic, the goal is to end with the iso of Oracle Linux on your local machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The version we will use here, will be Oracle Linux 6.3 x86_64, at some point will update the post to cover OL 6.4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will be divided in the following parts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 Some general information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 Downloading OL6 ISO from the mirrors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 Downloading OL6 ISO from e-delivery.oracle.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 Patches or yum repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Some general information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good source of information is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikis.oracle.com/display/oraclelinux/Home&quot;&gt;Oracle Linux Wiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will find useful information written from people close to Support, Marketing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle is a big company, so expect them to be sometimes slow, or some times you won't understand them at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is not just a Linux Company, is a end-to-end, or disk-to-app company. They do a lot of things, and keep buying companies to expand they offer. Real business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle, keep changing all the time, and the way they go to the market, keep changing also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be very frustrating for the new starterts, and a total challenge for the experts, but is part of the magic to work with Oracle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is not secret formula, there is no single source of truth with Oracle, what may work for someone, may not work at all for someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more important, what used to work, now doesn't work at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work with oracle require, test, test, test, test, test, test, test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best advise that I can share is, be nice, gentle and keep what you do under control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a bit messy in the test environment, then your dev environment will be a bit dirty, and when the time to push something into production came, you will be forced to acknowledge to put something in production that is not 100% nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may sound silly, and you may be thinking 'whatever, I am the linux ninja in my company' but in the Oracle world, the idea is keep the business running, keep the system up and running, and get uptime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I will share, a clean way, and will try to share my expertise here, and If you can use anything of this, I will be happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;/about.html&quot;&gt;about page&lt;/a&gt;, you will find my name, couple of links and my email. All feedback is welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Downloading OL6 ISO from the mirrors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Oracle Wiki, we can find there is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikis.oracle.com/display/oraclelinux/Downloading+Oracle+Linux&quot;&gt;list of mirrors&lt;/a&gt; from where download Oracle Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very nice, as you may have a mirror close to you, and it will be faster and simpler than using the Oracle Way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I am writing this, the mirror available are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Country     Mirror 
AU          AARnet  
                    http://mirror.aarnet.edu.au/pub/oraclelinux/
                    ftp://mirror.aarnet.edu.au/pub/oraclelinux/

DE 
            GWDG
                    http://ftp5.gwdg.de/pub/linux/oracle/
                    ftp://ftp5.gwdg.de/pub/linux/oracle/
                    rsync://ftp5.gwdg.de/pub/linux/oracle/

DE          NetCologne
                    http://mirror.netcologne.de/oracle-linux/
                    ftp://mirror.netcologne.de/oracle-linux/
                    rsync://mirror.netcologne.de/oracle-linux/ 
DK 
            dotsrc.org
                    http://mirrors.dotsrc.org/oracle-linux/
                    ftp://mirrors.dotsrc.org/oracle-linux/ 
FR 
            Institut de recherche et coordination acoustique/musique
                    http://mirrors.ircam.fr/pub/oraclelinux/
                    ftp://mirrors.ircam.fr/pub/oraclelinux/
                    rsync://mirrors.ircam.fr/pub/oraclelinux/
IE 
            HEAnet
                    http://ftp.heanet.ie/mirrors/oracle-linux/
                    ftp://ftp.heanet.ie/mirrors/oracle-linux/
                    rsync://ftp.heanet.ie/mirrors/oracle-linux/
PL 
            University of Warsaw - ICM
                    http://ftp.icm.edu.pl/pub/Linux/dist/oracle-linux/
                    ftp://ftp.icm.edu.pl/pub/Linux/dist/oracle-linux/
                    rsync://ftp.icm.edu.pl/pub/Linux/dist/oracle-linux/
UK 
            linux.org.uk
                    http://ftp.linux.org.uk/pub/distributions/enterprise/
                    ftp://ftp.linux.org.uk/pub/distributions/enterprise/
                    rsync://zeniv.linux.org.uk/distributions/enterprise/
US          Wimmekes.net
                    http://mirrors.wimmekes.net/pub/OracleLinux/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With great surprise I found this information when I had to download couple of isos.. I am located in NZ, and the internet here.. you get the idea.. so the mirror in Australia did the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an additional tip, the mirror on Wimmekes.net is one of the Senior VP of Oracle Linux, so chances that something show up there before the public-yum.oracle.com are very high time by time.. When that happen, he will update &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.oracle.com/wim/&quot;&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Downloading OL6 ISO from e-delivery.oracle.com&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle is a big company, because of this, you need to be prepared to login to some portals, click on some agreements (export, security, etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to avoid that, use wget/curl/script go with the mirrors, and all happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official source for distribution of Oracle Linux, OracleVM, and OracleVM Templates is on &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com/linux&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com/linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For other products you may find the source could be &lt;a href=&quot;http://otn.oracle.com&quot;&gt;otn.oracle.com&lt;/a&gt;, or in form of patches in &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.oracle.com&quot;&gt;support&lt;/a&gt;, or the general &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point you should register an account to become your oracle single sign on (sso) account, this account will be the same, for &lt;a href=&quot;http://otn.oracle.com&quot;&gt;otn.oracle.com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.oracle.com/&quot;&gt;forums&lt;/a&gt;, so when you get some time, create one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you got to &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com/linux&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com/linux&lt;/a&gt; you will see this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.27.31 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.27.31 PM.png' max-width='70%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you click on Sign in / Register button, you will redirected to the actual login / register page&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.29.01 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.29.01 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, highlighted in the red square is the part of the register. Follow the instructions, and you will be done with your account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point it will ask if you will like to get some emails with information. I find to be very nice the emails that oracle sent, so don't be shy and mark all the areas you are interested in. You will have the chance to opt out of those mails later if you don't like them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the account created, you can login.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the export regulation agrement, you will be on the main menu of &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com/linux&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com/linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.34.07 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.34.07 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your window is not the same, please check on top you are on Cloud Linux&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.34.55 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.34.55 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If not, probably you are in &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com&lt;/a&gt; instead of &lt;a href=&quot;http://edelivery.oracle.com/linux&quot;&gt;edelivery.oracle.com/linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then select the version and the architecture, here 6.3 x86_64 bits and click on GO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.36.53 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.36.53 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can click on the Oracle Linux Release 6 Update 3 Media Pack for x86_64 (64 bit) or select the radio button, scroll down and click on Continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you should see 6 options for Oracle Linux 6.3 x86_64&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.39.34 PM.png'&gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/kikitux.net 2013-02-27 at 5.39.34 PM.png' max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top Left of the option, there is a README button, in case of doubt, or just because you want to check, click on that, and have a look at the readme.  From here you have the option to download the isos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux Release 6 Update 3 for x86_64 (64 Bit)                       V33411-01   3.5G&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  The DVD to install the Oracle Linux 6.3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux Release 6 Update 3 Boot iso image for x86_64 (64 bit)        V33412-01   198M&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  The boot.iso image to use this same iso to boot from hard disk or network (ftp, http or nfs)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux Release 6 Update 3 source DVD 1                              V33413-01   3.1G&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux Release 6 Update 3 source DVD 2                              V33414-01   1.7G&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  The sources, source rpm of the content of the media&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux Release 6 Update 3 UEK Boot ISO image for x86_64 (64 bit)    V34537-01   196M&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  A second boot.iso, this one is to be able to use btrfs as a filesystem option during the install.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the README are the instructions on how to use the UEK Boot ISO image for x86_64, those instruction are are very clear on how to prepare a network point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a separate post, I will cover how to do this, and how to create a new Oracle Linux 6.3 ISO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you will like to try this, without all the problems to extract the iso, modified, recreate one, you may try an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/waht5bii6nchkrd/OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-btrfs.iso&quot;&gt;ISO image that I have created&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other resources, check what I have shared &lt;a href=&quot;/dropbox&quot;&gt;on dropbox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main difference is, you can actually choose btrfs from the installer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will cover this option, and some examples on btrfs in a separate post, however, if you google about btrfs you will see all the nice features this have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Patches or yum repository&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux is one of those RedHat derivates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won't go deep on here, and won't compare with CentOS or other RedHat derivates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to Oracle Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle Linux is based on RPM, that is RedHat Package Management. The tool to use RPM is the command rpm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RPM works very great that is used by other Linux distros (like Suse) and even some other Unix (AIX use some packages on RPM format).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, the rpm had a downside, that was the dependency nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You wanted to install patch A, and you found patch A, require patch B, and patch B required patch C and D, and so on..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may ended downloading 15 patches on different versions to then find the new versions conflict with the existing ones due versions, so you had to say I will update the installed one (and end updating say 50 rpms) or re-download rpms again to match the ones installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real 'fun'&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, the guys at Yellow Dog came with the YUM, Yellow Dog Update Manager, YUM, that basically used an external database to track versions and dependencies and with a repository, it will download and take of the nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the version 4 of the distro, YUM was external. Once the system was installed you can use it.. very nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For version 5 of the distro, the YUM came included at the moment of the install, so once the OS was installed, you pointed the new fresh machine to a yum repo, and you can update immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the version 6, now this is cool, you can point to a yum repository during the install (interactive by a menu, or automated by a kickstart file) and instead of using the packages of the DVD or the network share, it will install the updates one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may sound similar, but let's check on times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On version 5, say install 20 minutes, boot, full update 20 minutes, boot. Total 40 minutes and 1 reboot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On version 6, say install 20 mins.. boot.. done.. Updated. Total 20 mins no reboot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For oracle linux, the public source of repo is &lt;a href=&quot;http://public-yum.oracle.com&quot;&gt;public-yum.oracle.com&lt;/a&gt; in the web page are the instructions, and work very very nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a new installed machine, with direct access to internet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Oracle Linux 6

# cd /etc/yum.repos.d
# wget http://public-yum.oracle.com/public-yum-ol6.repo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With no direct access to internet, say with a proxy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Oracle Linux 6

# cd /etc/yum.repos.d
# http_proxy=http://proxy:3128 wget http://public-yum.oracle.com/public-yum-ol6.repo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just replace proxy:3128 with the correct url of the proxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a later post I will post information how to use an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kikitux/public-yum-downloader&quot;&gt;script I wrote to create a local yum repo from public-yum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this you have now all the information to download your Oracle Linux iso, and keep the system updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;What's next&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check the new post &lt;a href=&quot;http://kikitux.net/vbox/creating-an-oracle-linux-6-virtualbox-guest.html&quot;&gt;how to create a virtual machine&lt;/a&gt; with virtualbox&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alvaro.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>zsync</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/zsync/zsync.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-25T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/zsync/zsync</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been testing zsync and it's great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href=&quot;/zsync&quot;&gt;download from here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's see an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have 2 isos, the normal oracle linux 6.3 dvd and one modified to be able to use btrfs from the installer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both dvd are just the same, few bits different, according to zsync, 97% the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download the normal dvd iso&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;retina:tmp mirandaa$ zsync http://mirandaa00/stage/iso/OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-dvd.iso.zsync
#################### 100.0% 0.0 kBps DONE    

No relevent local data found - I will be downloading the whole file. If that's not what you want, CTRL-C out. You should specify the local file is the old version of the file to download with -i (you might have to decompress it with gzip -d first). Or perhaps you just have no data that helps download the file
downloading from http://mirandaa00/stage/iso/OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-dvd.iso:
#################### 100.0% 102257.5 kBps DONE     

verifying download...checksum matches OK
used 0 local, fetched 3675326805
retina:tmp mirandaa$ ls
OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-dvd.iso
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;let's move the normal dvd into the btrfs one&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;retina:tmp mirandaa$ mv OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-dvd.iso OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-btrfs.iso 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let's use zsync to update the normal dvd into the modified one&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;retina:tmp mirandaa$ zsync http://mirandaa00/stage/iso/OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-btrfs.iso.zsync
#################### 100.0% 0.0 kBps DONE    

reading seed file OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-btrfs.iso: *************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************************Read OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-btrfs.iso. Target 97.1% complete.      
downloading from http://mirandaa00/stage/iso/OracleLinux-R6-U3-Server-x86_64-btrfs.iso:
#################### 100.0% 9790.2 kBps DONE      

verifying download...checksum matches OK
used 3598319616 local, fetched 108470391
retina:tmp mirandaa$ 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alvaro&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>OL6 Certified Implementation Specialist</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/cert/ol6-certified-implementation-specialist.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-25T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/cert/ol6-certified-implementation-specialist</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back on December I took the 1z1-460 exam for Oracle Linux 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday, got a letter from Oracle with a printed certificate, quite nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks Oracle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;digital&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/OEL 6 Implementation Specialist 2012.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/OEL 6 Implementation Specialist 2012.png&quot; max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;paper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/OEL 6 Implementation Specialist 2012 - carton.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/2013/02/OEL 6 Implementation Specialist 2012 - carton.jpg&quot; max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>zfs data protection</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/zfs/zfs-data-protection.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-22T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/zfs/zfs-data-protection</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When ZFS for MAC came out with ZEVO, I did run to get the software and being used for about a year or so..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you stay away enabling dedup, the filesystem run very good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I did format a 500gb disk to use for some VM's in my laptop. If those VM's die, it's ok, I usually have VirtualBox appliances, and backup of the software, so I could be able to start from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I will like to protect the whole disk file without having to backup, in case I drop the hdd (again), and some blocks came corrupted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did use the zfs option to have more copies stored on disk, in this case 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Disk just formatted&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;retina:~ mirandaa$ zfs get copies
NAME      PROPERTY  VALUE   SOURCE
zfs500gb  copies    1       local&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Enable the option copy=2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;retina:~ mirandaa$ zfs set copies=2 zfs500gb
retina:~ mirandaa$ zfs get copies
NAME      PROPERTY  VALUE   SOURCE
zfs500gb  copies    2       local&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;let's write some data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;100MB&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;retina:~ mirandaa$ df -h /Volumes/zfs500gb/
Filesystem   Size   Used  Avail Capacity iused     ifree %iused  Mounted on
/dev/disk2  457Gi  354Ki  457Gi     1%      70 957873343    0%   /Volumes/zfs500gb
retina:~ mirandaa$ dd if=/dev/zero of=/Volumes/zfs500gb/file bs=1024000 count=100
100+0 records in
100+0 records out
102400000 bytes transferred in 0.067305 secs (1521435685 bytes/sec)
retina:~ mirandaa$ df -h /Volumes/zfs500gb/
Filesystem   Size   Used  Avail Capacity iused     ifree %iused  Mounted on
/dev/disk2  457Gi  196Mi  457Gi     1%      71 957472837    0%   /Volumes/zfs500gb
retina:~ mirandaa$ ls -alh /Volumes/zfs500gb/file 
-rw-r--r--  1 mirandaa  staff    98M 22 Feb 13:31 /Volumes/zfs500gb/file
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1GB&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;retina:~ mirandaa$ dd if=/dev/zero of=/Volumes/zfs500gb/file bs=1024000 count=1000
1000+0 records in
1000+0 records out
1024000000 bytes transferred in 32.551312 secs (31458025 bytes/sec)
retina:~ mirandaa$ df -h /Volumes/zfs500gb/
Filesystem   Size   Used  Avail Capacity iused     ifree %iused  Mounted on
/dev/disk2  457Gi  1.9Gi  455Gi     1%      71 953981891    0%   /Volumes/zfs500gb
retina:~ mirandaa$ ls -alh /Volumes/zfs500gb/file 
-rw-r--r--  1 mirandaa  staff   977M 22 Feb 13:32 /Volumes/zfs500gb/file
retina:~ mirandaa$ 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system, is transparent, just just get more used space, and less free space:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='/images/kikitux.net 2013-02-22 at 1.42.08 PM.png' &gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/kikitux.net 2013-02-22 at 1.42.08 PM.png'  max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='/images/kikitux.net 2013-02-22 at 1.41.49 PM.png' &gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/kikitux.net 2013-02-22 at 1.41.49 PM.png'  max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an excerpt from an oracle post &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.oracle.com/relling/entry/zfs_copies_and_data_protection&quot;&gt;https://blogs.oracle.com/relling/entry/zfs_copies_and_data_protection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Using Copies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To change the numbers of data copies, set the copies property. For example, suppose I have a zpool named &quot;zwimming.&quot; The default number of data copies is 1. But you can change that to 2 quite easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# zfs set copies=2 zwimming
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The copies property works for all new writes, so I recommend that you set that policy when you create the file system or immediately after you create a zpool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can verify the copies setting by looking at the properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# zfs get copies zwimming
NAME      PROPERTY  VALUE     SOURCE
zwimming  copies    2         local
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ZFS will account for the space used. For example, suppose I create three new file systems and copy some data to them. You can then see that the space used reflects the number of copies. If you use quotas, then the copies will be charged against the quotas, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# zfs create -o copies=1 zwimming/single
# zfs create -o copies=2 zwimming/dual
# zfs create -o copies=3 zwimming/triple
# cp -rp /usr/share/man1 /zwimming/single
# cp -rp /usr/share/man1 /zwimming/dual
# cp -rp /usr/share/man1 /zwimming/triple
# zfs list -r zwimming                                                       
NAME              USED  AVAIL  REFER  MOUNTPOINT
zwimming         48.2M   310M  33.5K  /zwimming
zwimming/dual    16.0M   310M  16.0M  /zwimming/dual
zwimming/single  8.09M   310M  8.09M  /zwimming/single
zwimming/triple  23.8M   310M  23.8M  /zwimming/triple
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes sense. Each file system has one, two, or three copies of the data and will use correspondingly one, two, or three times as much space to store the data.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>SQL Staments</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/sql/sql-staments.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-21T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/sql/sql-staments</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Data manipulation language (DML)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;SELECT
INSERT
UPDATE
DELETE
MERGE
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Data definition language (DDL)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;CREATE
ALTER
DROP
RENAME
TRUNCATE
COMMENT
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Data control language (DCL)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;GRANT
REVOKE
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Transaction control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;COMMIT
ROLLBACK
SAVEPOINT
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>HR Schema</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/oracle/hr-schema.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-21T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/oracle/hr-schema</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;HR Schema in Oracle sample database&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/oracle/hr.png' &gt;&lt;img src='https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/oracle/hr.png'  max-width='99%' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alvaro&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>OSX server and ruby dependencies</title>
   <link href="http://kikitux.net/osx/osx-server-and-ruby-dependencies.html"/>
   <updated>2013-02-14T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>http://kikitux.net/osx/osx-server-and-ruby-dependencies</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a person who likes to have backups, and be on the bleeding edge most of the time, testing, checking.. learnings.. even when that mean break my database box at the office and also found that yesterdy update of ruby at my mac mini server &lt;a href=&quot;http://support.apple.com/kb/TS4042&quot;&gt;broke the ruby dependencies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wondering how long it will take break my mac server anyways.. took, 2 days.. :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/kikitux/kikitux.github.com/master/images/osx/Server.png&quot; title=&quot;Osx Server&quot; alt=&quot;OSX Server&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alvaro&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>